Preliminary Guide to the Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers Papers, 1970 - 1980
Duke University. University Archives
Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers papers 1970 - 1980
Meyers, Carol L. Meyers, Eric M.
16.5 linear feet Extent: 16,500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers are professors in Duke University's Department of Religion. Throughout their careers, they have conducted archeological digs in relation to their interest in biblical and Judaic studies. The Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers Papers contain materials related to several major excavations the pair conducted in Israel in the 1970s. The materials in the collection include binders and notebooks of notes, charts, and records; notecards; photographs; coins; and drawings. Topics include archaeology, the Meiron, Khirbet Shema, and Gush Halav sites in Israel, biblical studies, Jewish artifacts, and ancient artifacts. English.
UA.29.02.0027
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1982; 1988; 1994; 2003.
Biographical Note
Eric M. and Carol L. Meyers are both professors in the Department of Religion at Duke University.
Eric M. Meyers joined Duke in 1969, after receiving his Ph.D. from Harvard University. Since joining the faculty of Duke, Eric Meyers has published extensively in the fields of biblical archeology and Judaism, often collaborating with wife Carol Meyers. He has also directed many archeological excavations in Israel and Italy. Eric Meyers is now Bernice and Morton Lerner Professor of Judaic Studies, and directs the Graduate Program in Religion.
Carol L. Meyers received her Ph.D. from Brandeis University, and joined Duke in 1977. Like her husband, Carol Meyers also focuses on biblical archeology and biblical studies, and is especially interested in the role of women in the biblical world. She has published widely, and directs many archeological excavations. She is Co-Director of Duke's Summer in Israel Program, and also directs undergraduate studies in the Duke Department of Religion. The holder of the Mary Grace Wilson Professorship in Religion, Carol Meyers is also an affiated faculty member in the Women Studies Program at Duke.
Collection Overview
The collection (A82-72, A88-0040, A94-116) includes binders, notebooks, notecards, photographs, and drawings related to major Israeli archeological digs in Meiron and Khribet Shema. Materials have been kept in the binders and folders in which they were received. The collection is organized by accession number, but materials in separate accession number groups are intrinsically connected.
The addition (A2003-30) includes binders from an archeological dig in Gush Halav, and Arabic and Jewish coins from the Meiron and Khirbet Shema digs.
Subject Headings
Archaeology; Archaeology and religion; Bible -- Study and teaching; Coins; Coins, Arab; Coins, Jewish; Duke University. Dept. of Religion; Excavations (Archaeology); Excavations (Archaeology) -- Israel -- Meron; Gush Halav Site (Israel); Israel -- Antiquities; Jews -- Antiquities; Meron (Israel) -- Antiquities; Meyers, Carol L.; Meyers, Eric M.; Photographs; Shema Site (Israel)
Contents of Collection
- Accession Number 82-72
  These materials contain information about the Meyerses' digs in Meiron and Khirbet Shema in Israel during the early and mid-1970s. These notes and records were later used as sources for two books co-written by the Meyerses, Excavations at Ancient Meiron, Upper Galilee, Israel 1971-72, 1974-75, 1977, and Ancient Synagogue Excavations at Khirbet Shema, Upper Galilee, Israel 1970-1972. The letters and numbers used to identify the various binders and folders (i.e. MV 4) indicate a particular physical part of the excavation site. Only some of the binders and folders are dated.
  - MV 1, 2, 3, 4 (Box 1)
  - MV 4 (Box 1)
  - MBI 1, 3 (Box 1)
  - MBI 2 (Box 1)
  - MV 5, 1975 (Box 1)
  - MVI (Box 1)
  - MVII 3 (Box 1)
  - MVII 2, 1977 (Box 1)
  - MVII 1, 1977 (Box 1)
  - C-6 (MI 3) and C-7 (MVII 1), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - MI 2, 1975 (Box 2)
  - MII 4, 1977 (Box 2)
  - MIV 2, 1974 (Box 2)
  - C-1 (MIII 4) and C-2, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - MII 3, 1977 (Box 2)
  - MII 5 (Box 2)
  - MI 3, 1975 (Box 2)
  - MI 4 (Box 2)
  - MIII 3, 6, 7 (Box 2)
  - MIII 4, 5 (Box 2)
  - Photos, M, 2", 1974 (Box 3)
  - M, B&W [photos], 1975 (Box 3)
  - M, 35mm photos, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - MIII, 1, 2 (Box 3)
  - MI 5 (Box 4)
  - MI 6 (Box 4)
  - MI 1, 3 (Box 4)
  - MI 2 (Box 4)
  - MI 2, 8 (Box 4)
  - MI 7, 8 (Box 4)
  - MI 1, 2, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Field notebooks for Khirbet Shema excavation, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
  - Field notebooks for Khirbet Shema excavation, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - [Khirbet Shema Weekly Reports], 1971 (Box 7)
  - Meiron Weekly Reports, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Meiron Weekly Reports, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Meiron Pottery Readings and Critical Locus List, 1974 (Box 7)
  - [Khibet Shema Weekly Reports (4 binders)], 1970-1971 (Box 7)
  - Khibet Shema Registry, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
- Accession number A88-0040
  These 6.5" x 9" registry cards were produced to document artifacts found at the Khirbet Shema and Meiron archeological sites in Israel in the 1970s. Some of the cards feature pencil drawings of the objects.
  - Registry cards for artifacts from Khirbet Shema and Meiron sites, 1970-1977 (Box 7)
- Accession number A94-116
  These field notebooks from the Khirbet Shema excavation in Israel date from 1971. The letters and numbers used to identify the notebooks indicate specific physical places at the excavation site.
  - NW VII.27, 1971 (Box 7)
  - SE II.8[15], 1971 (Box 7)
  - SE II.1[7-8], 1971 (Box 7)
  - SE II.7[14], 1971 (Box 7)
- Accession number A2003-30
  - Gush Halav binders (Box 8)
    - I.1, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - I.2, 1978 (Box 8)
    - I.3, 1977 (Box 8)
    - I.4, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - I.5, 1977 (Box 8)
    - I.6, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Khirbet Shema coin samples, 1970-1974 (Box 9)
  - Meiron coin samples, 1977 (Box 10)
  - Khirbet Shema coin samples, 1970-1975 (Box 10)
  - Photo File, Coin Negatives, 1977 (Box 11)
  - Transcript of Conference with Ya'akov Meshorer on Meiron, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Tyrian Influence in the Upper Galilee, by Richard S. Hanson, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Khirbet Shema coin samples, 1971-1974 (Box 11)
  - Meiron coin samples, 1977 (Box 11)
  - Khirbet Shema Arabic coin samples, 1970-1971 (Box 11)